Finding Aid for Office of Medical Development and Alumni Relations (University of Michigan) records, 1875-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of Medical Development and Alumni Relations (University of Michigan) records 1875-2001, 1960-2001
University of Michigan. Office of Medical Development and Alumni Relations.
5.5 linear feet
02112 Bimu 2
Unit responsible for fundraising and event programming involving alumni of the University of Michigan Medical Center and Health System. Includes topical files, Medical Center Alumni Society meeting records, and photographs and videotapes of development events and programs, including named professorship dedications.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 9098 ) was received from the unit in July 2001.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
The Office of Medical Development and Alumni Relations is responsible for fundraising and interaction with alumni for the University of Michigan Medical Center, including the University of Michigan Hospitals and Medical School. Over the years, the office has sponsored a variety of fundraising and programming events that are documented within these records. The New Horizons in Medicine program (1992 to 1995) was a series of special programs developed to bring major and prospective donors to campus to learn about medical research, education, and patient care, as well as to cultivate them as donors for the MomentUM capital campaign. The Vital Signs program (1987) was a series of one-day seminars designed to inform and broaden the interest of potential donors and friends of the Medical Center. The Luncheon Program (1991 to 1993) was designed to bring together prospective donors, business leaders and other individuals from the local community to meet with the Executive Director of the University of Michigan Hospitals, and the Vice Provost for Medical Affairs.
The Medical Center Alumni Society (MCAS) was founded in 1960, as an affiliate of the Alumni Association of the University of Michigan, as one of the first alumni societies at Michigan whose membership consisted of graduates of a particular school or college. Staffing for the MCAS organization and activities is currently provided by the Office of Medical Development and Alumni Relations, but has in the past been assigned to other administrative units, including the Alumni Association and the Office of Postgraduate Medicine (Department of Medical Education.)
MCAS membership is open to graduates of the Medical School and its related residency, fellowship, and doctoral programs, past and present Medical School faculty members, as well as those who have demonstrated an interest in the Medical Center. Membership included the School of Nursing alumni and faculty members until the School of Nursing officially withdrew from MCAS as of January 1, 1993. MCAS membership is granted automatically; no membership dues are assessed.
The Board of Governors is the governing arm of MCAS. Sixteen members of the board are chosen by election, serving three-year terms (ten members are graduates of the Medical School, and the remaining six may be graduates of the Medical School, graduate training programs, or past and present faculty members). A number of ex officio members represent university administrative units. Meeting semi-annually, the Board of Governors is organized into committees, where the work of the organization is conducted. Current committees consist of the Executive, Awards and Nominating, Reunion and Alumni Programs, and Student-Alumni Relations Committees. Past committees have included Development-Outreach, Reunion-Departmental Relations, and Directory/Database committees.
A Visiting Committee reported to the Board of Governors from 1974 to around the time of a constitutional change in the early 1990s. The Visiting Committee consisted of a group of 16 appointed members (both alumni and national health care leaders) that met annually to make strategic planning and operational recommendations to administrators of the Medical Center.
MCAS sponsors a number of activities, including the annual MCAS reunion each fall, an awards program honoring distinguished alumni, scholarships for deserving students in the health professions, and outreach activities for alumni and students. MCAS activities are funded from gifts as well as budget appropriation from the University of Michigan Alumni Association.
The Office of Medical Development and Alumni Relations records (5.5 linear feet) date from 1960 to 2001 and are organized into three series: Topical Files, Medical Center Alumni Society (MCAS) Files, and Audiovisual Materials. The records include programs, photographs, minutes, reports and videos reflecting programming and educational activities and the changing organizational structure and mission of the Office of Medical Development and Alumni Relations over time.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Office of Medical Development and Alumni Relations.; Educational fund raising--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan. Medical Center.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.; University of Michigan. Health System.; University of Michigan. Medical Center. Alumni Society.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Office of Medical Development and Alumni Relations.; University of Michigan. Medical Center.; University of Michigan. Health System.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.; Campaign for Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Topical Files
  The series Topical Files, 1983-1999 (.75 linear feet), is an alphabetically arranged sequence containing materials related to the daily work of the Office of Medical Development and Alumni Relations. The events files include programs, guest lists, and correspondence related to the many programs sponsored and organized by the office, revealing the development of the office's strategies for cultivating alumni and for fundraising.
  - Endowed Scholarships, Fellowships and Professorships Listing 1999 (Box 1)
  - Events
    - Donor Relations Dinners 1989-1994, 4 folders (Box 1)
      (includes photographs)
    - Inaugural Professorships
      - E. Gifford and Love Barnett Upjohn Professorship in Internal Medicine and Oncology 1991
        - Correspondence and Program (Box 1)
        - Video (VHS) (Housed in Box 6) (Box 1)
      - Emanuel Maisel Professorship of Oncology 1991 (includes photograph) (Box 1)
      - George G. Morley Professorship Campaign 1994 (Box 1)
      - Percy and Mary Murphy Professorship of Pediatrics and Child Health Delivery, Video 1999 (VHS) (Housed in Box 6) (Box 1)
      - Ralph Waldo Gerard Professorship of Neurosciences 1991
        - Correspondence and Program (Box 1)
        - Video (VHS) (Housed in Box 6) (Box 1)
      - Richard C. Schneider Professorship in Neurosurgery 1993 (Box 1)
      - Warner-Lambert/Parke-Davis Professorships in Medicine 1994 (Box 1)
    - John and Suzanne Munn Endowment, Video 1990 (U-matic) (Housed in Box 6) (Box 1)
    - Luncheon Program
      - Forsyth Lunches 1993 (Box 1)
      - Zuidema Lunches 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - MomentUM Campaign
      - Briefing 1991 (includes negatives from Kickoff Reception) (Box 1)
      - Kickoff 1992 (Box 1)
      - Videos
        - Full-Screen Version 1992 (VHS and U-matic formats) (Housed in Box 6) (Box 1)
        - G Version 1992 (U-matic) (Housed in Box 6) (Box 1)
    - New Horizons in Medicine 1992-1995
      - May 7-9, 1992 (Box 1)
      - May 6-8, 1993 (Box 1)
      - May 12-14, 1994 (Box 1)
      - May 12-13, 1995 (Box 1)
      - October 21-23 circa 1996 (Box 1)
    - Replacement Hospital Project
      - Donor Recognition 1988 (Box 1)
      - Memorials in Old Main, NACB and SACB 1985 (Box 1)
      - Slide Show Video 1983 (U-matic) (Housed in Box 6) (Box 1)
    - Vital Signs Seminars
      - Correspondence and Programs 1987 (Box 1)
      - Videos 1989 (VHS and U-matic) (Housed in Box 6) (Box 1)
  - History of Medical School circa 1999 (Box 1)
  - Medical School Sesquicentennial Planning Guide 1999 (Box 1)
- Medical Center Alumni Society (MCAS) Files
  The Medical Center Alumni Society (MCAS) Files series, 1960-2001, (3.75 linear feet), is an alphabetically arranged series containing materials related to MCAS. The files include minutes, programs, membership rosters, and correspondence from the semi-annual meetings of the Board of Governors as well as the annual meetings of the Visiting Committee, providing an in-depth look at the operation of the organization and changes in its structure and focus. Also included in the Board of Governors annual meeting files are reports from a number of campus leaders, including the Dean of the Medical School, the Executive Director of the University Hospitals, the Vice Provost For Medical Affairs, and through the early 1990s, the Dean of the School of Nursing. These reports serve well to identify important issues of the time.
  - Alumni Fund, final reports 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Background and History
    - Constitution 1985, 1988 (See also Board of Governors Meeting Folders in Boxes 1-3) (Box 1)
    - Constitution and By-Laws Committee 1988 (Box 1)
    - MCAS Governance History 1960-1979 (Box 1)
    - MCAS History 1970-1987 (Box 1)
    - Medical Alumni Association of the University of Michigan, Facsimile of 1st Meeting Minutes 1875 (Box 1)
    - New business 1985 (Box 1)
      (information for new Society members)
    - Orientation Book for New Board Members 1997 (Box 1)
    - Visiting Committee History 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Board of Governors Meetings
    - July 7, 1968 (Box 1)
    - February 25, 1978 (Box 1)
    - October 5, 1978 (Box 1)
    - February 24, 1979 (Box 1)
    - October 11, 1979 (Box 1)
    - February 23, 1980 (Box 1)
    - September 25, 1980 (Box 2)
    - March 7, 1981 (Box 2)
    - October 15, 1981 (Box 2)
    - June 5, 1982 (Box 2)
    - September 30, 1982 (Box 2)
    - October 13, 1983 (Box 2)
    - June 16, 1984 (Box 2)
    - September 13, 1984 (Box 2)
    - June 15, 1985 (Box 2)
    - October 3, 1985 (Box 2)
    - May 31, 1986 (Box 2)
    - September 18, 1986 (Box 2)
    - May 30, 1987 (Box 2)
    - September 24, 1987 (Box 2)
    - May 7, 1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - November 4, 1988 (Box 2)
    - May 13, 1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - November 3, 1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - May 12, 1990, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - May 11, 1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - November 1, 1991, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - May 9, 1992 (Box 3)
    - November 13, 1992 (Box 3)
    - May 8, 1993 (Box 3)
    - November 12, 1993, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - May 7, 1994, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - May 19, 1995 (Box 3)
    - October 5, 1995 (Box 3)
    - March 29, 1996, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - September 26, 1997 (Box 3)
    - March 21, 1997 (Box 3)
    - September 18, 1997 (Box 3)
    - March 21, 1997 (Box 3)
    - September 18, 1997 (Box 3)
    - March 20, 1998 (Box 3)
    - September 10. 1998 (Box 3)
    - March 19, 1999 (Box 3)
    - September 30, 1999 (Box 3)
    - March 23, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Conferences
    - Medical Center Alumni Society conference 1947-1966 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters
    - Michigan Medical Center Alumni newsletter, 1963-1965 (Box 3)
    - Medical Center Alumni news, 1974-1980 (Box 3)
  - Parents Weekend 1989-1992, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Reunion
    - Brochures 1947-1966 (Box 4)
    - 1984-1985, 1987-1992, 1996, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Review
    - Ad hoc Review Committee
      - Meetings
        - March 27, 1987 (Box 4)
        - April 3, 1987 (Box 4)
        - April 10, 1987 (Box 4)
        - July 13, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Retreat 1987, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Report June 15, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Awards Review Committee 1987-1988 (Box 4)
    - Nominating Review Committee 1987-1988 (Box 4)
    - Outreach Review Committee 1987-1988 (Box 4)
    - Reunion Review Committee 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - Visiting Committee Meetings
    - 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1976 (Box 4)
    - 1977, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1978 (Box 4)
    - 1979, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1980 (Box 4)
    - 1981, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1982 (Box 5)
    - 1983 (Box 5)
    - 1984 (Box 5)
    - 1985, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1987, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1988, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1989 (Box 5)
    - 1990 (Box 5)
    - 1991 (Box 5)
    - 1992 (Box 5)
    - 1993 (includes photograph) (Box 5)
    - 1994 (includes photograph) (Box 5)
- Audiovisual Materials
  The Audiovisual Materials series, 1983-1999, (1.0 linear feet), contains a number of videos created for events sponsored by the office, as well as videos that document events planned by the office. This series provides a visual context for the work of the office.
  - Audio Cassettes
    - Health Care in the Crucible Audiocassettes undated, 2 audiocassettes (Box 5)
  - Videos
    - Campaign for Michigan Videos 1992 (VHS and U-matic) (Box 5)
    - Cancer Center Television Reports (WDIV Detroit) undated (U-matic) (Box 5)
    - Capital Campaign Kickoff Compilation Video 1992 (VHS) (Box 5)
    - E. Gifford and Love Barnett Upjohn Professorship in Internal Medicine and Oncology, Video 1991 (VHS) (Box 5)
    - Percy and Mary Murphy Professorship of Pediatrics and Child Health Delivery, Video 1999 (VHS) (Box 5)
    - Ralph Waldo Gerard Professorship of Neurosciences Video 1991 (VHS) (Box 5)
    - John and Suzanne Munn Endowment Video 1990 (U-matic) (Box 5)
    - MomentUM Campaign Videos
      - Full-Screen Version 1992 (VHS and U-matic) (Box 5)
      - G Version 1992 (U-matic) (Box 5)
    - Replacement Hospital Capital Campaign Slide Show Video 1983 (U-matic) (Box 5)
    - Vital Signs Seminar Videos 1989 (VHS and U-matic) (Box 5)
Related Material
Additional material held by the Bentley Library relating to Medical Center Alumni Society activities include: UM Medical School records, UM Vice Provost for Medical Affairs records, UM Hospitals records, and UM School of Nursing records. Additional documentation within these records relates to other alumni and development activities and events.